NAHEED ANJUM ARAFAT

Research Fellow, Department of Information Systems and Analytics, National University of Singapore

email: naheed_anjum@u.nus.edu | website: https://toggled.github.io/naheed | contact: +65-90196390

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in the algorithmic and applied aspects of graph and hypergraph structured data and topological approaches for data analysis. I am also interested in the synergy between machine learning and network analysis. I have worked on the following topics over the years-

- Graphs: Co-evolution of software ecosystem networks. Topological analysis of graph structured data.
- Hypergraphs: Algorithms for generating and estimating properties of random hypergraphs with a prescribed constraint. Algorithms for visualising hypergraphs.
- Topological data analysis: Exact and approximate computation of topological features of Euclidean and graph data.
- Optimisation: Evolutionary algorithms for solving many-objective optimisation problems.

EDUCATION

National University of Singapore (NUS)

Singapore

PhD in Computer Science

Aug 2015 - Present (Thesis defended)

• Thesis: Analysis and generation of data with topology from combinatorial representations

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Bachelors in Computer Science & Engineering; GPA: 3.79/4

May 2014

• Thesis: A Fuzzy Dominance Based Evolutionary Algorithm for solving many-objective optimisation problems.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Research Fellow Singapore

Department of Information Systems & Analytics, NUS

July 2020 - Present

Research Assistant Singapore

Department of Computer Science, NUS

Nov 2019 - June 2020

Full-time LecturerDhaka, BangladeshDepartment of Computer Science, United International UniversityJun 2014 - Jul 2015

but 2017 but 2018

Part-time DeveloperDhaka, BangladeshSoftware Global ConsultancyJan 2014 - Mar 2014

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Fellow Department of Information Systems & Analytics, NUS

Mentor: Assistant Professor UM Sungyong July 2020 - Present

• **Project:** Co-evolution of software ecosystem networks.

Research Assistant Department of Computer Science, NUS

Mentor: Professor Tan Kian Lee Nov 2019 - June 2020

 $\bullet\,$ Project: Random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed constraints.

PhD Student Department of Computer Science, NUS

PhD Supervisor: Associate Professor Stéphane Bressan Jan 2016 - Present

Undergraduate research Department of CSE, BUET

Supervisor: Professor Md Monirul Islam

Jan 2013 - May 2014

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate Assistant NUS

Jan 2016 - 2019 As a graduate teaching assistant, I conducted weekly tutorials and held student consultation sessions.

• Courses-

- o Big Data Techniques and Technologies (BT4221): Department Of Information Systems and Analytics, School of Computing Semester
- o Data Management and Warehousing (BT5110): Master Of Science Business Analytics Programme Semester 1 of 2019, 2018 and 2017.
- o Information Visualisation (CS5346): Department of Computer Science, School of Computing Semester 2, 2018.
- Discrete Structures (CS1231): Department of Computer Science, School of Computing Semester 1, 2016.
- Programming Methodology (CS1010E): Department of Computer Science, School of Computing Semester 2 of 2017 and 2016.

Lecturer

United International University

Jun 2014 - Jul 2015 As a full-time lecturer, I designed module curriculum, prepared lecture notes, assignments and exam questions, delivered lectures, conducted lab-sessions, and evaluated assignment submissions and exam-scripts. I was also involved in various administrative duties.

Courses-

- o Advanced Programming Languages: Summer 2014, Fall 2014, Spring 2015, Summer 2015 trimesters.
- o Data Structures: Fall 2014. Summer 2015 trimesters.
- o Discrete Mathematics: Summer 2014 trimester.
- Structured Programming Language: Spring 2015 trimester.
- o Electric Circuits: Fall 2014, Spring 2015, Summer 2015 trimesters.

Mentor NUS

I held consultation and discussion sessions to assist students in their research.

Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

o Debabrata Mahapatra: PhD lab-rotation under Stéphane Bressan.

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

• Conference Proceedings

- 1. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, Laurent Decreusefond, and Stéphane Bressan. Construction and random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed degree and dimension sequences. In Database and Expert Systems Applications, pages 130–145, Cham, 2020. Springer International Publishing
- 2. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, and Stéphane Bressan. Topological data analysis with ϵ -net induced lazy witness complex. In Database and Expert Systems Applications, pages 376-392, Cham, 2019. Springer International Publishing
- 3. Naheed Anjum Arafat and Stéphane Bressan. Hypergraph drawing by force-directed placement. In International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications, pages 387-394, Cham, 2017. Springer International Publishing

Journals

1. Siddhartha Shankar Das, Md Monirul Islam, and Naheed Anjum Arafat. Evolutionary algorithm using adaptive fuzzy dominance and reference point for many-objective optimization. Swarm and evolutionary computation, 44:1092-1107, 2019

Preprints

1. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, Laurent Decreusefond, and Stéphane Bressan. Construction and random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed degree and dimension sequences (extended version). arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.05429, 2020

Workshops/Posters

1. Naheed Anjum Arafat, Debabrota Basu, and Stéphane Bressan. ϵ -net induced lazy witness complexes on graphs. Workshop on Applications of Topological Data Analysis (ATDA), held in conjunction with ECML-PKDD, 2019

TALKS

Guest Lectures:

- Big Data Techniques and Technologies module (NUS): I delivered two guest lectures on 'Practical data analysis using Amazon EMR and Sagemaker services' during Semester 1, 2020 offering of undergraduate module BT4221.
- o Data Management and Warehousing module (NUS): I delivered a hands-on lecture on 'developing retail-sales data mart using Pentaho' during Semester 1, 2018 offering of masters module BT5111.

• **Information visualisation module (NUS):** I delivered a guest lecture on 'Graph and hypergraph data visualisation tools' during Semester 2, 2018 offering of masters module CS5346.

• Seminar Talks:

- DEXA 2020: I presented my paper on Construction and random generation of hypergraphs with prescribed degree and dimension sequences
- **DEXA 2019:** I presented my paper on *Topological data analysis with* ϵ *-net induced lazy witness complex.*
- E2S2-CREATE Seminar: I gave a talk on *Topological Data Analysis* at E2S2-CREATE Seminar, Feb 2018 attended by 20+ researchers from E2S2 project funded by NRF.

ACADEMIC SERVICES

• Reviewer: SKIMA 2014

- External Reviewer: DASFAA 2020, DAWAK 2020, ICDE 2018, VLDB 2017, DEXA 2017.
- Co-organiser: Co-organised 8th International Conference on Software, Knowledge, Information Management and Applications (SKIMA), 2014 held at United International University, Bangladesh.
- Session Chair: Chaired two sessions at NUS SoC-Telecom ParisTech joint workshop on Data Sciences and Artificial Intelligence, April 2018 attended by 20+ researchers from Telecom ParisTech and NUS.
- Session Chair: Chaired two sessions at NUS School of Computing Research Workshop, March 2018 attended by professors and researchers from various countries in Asia.

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- NUS Research Scholarship for PhD students (2015-2019).
- Teaching Assistant Training Certificate issued by the Centre for Development of Teaching & Learning (CDTL), NUS for completing training on applying 'Collaborative Learning' approaches.
- **Distinguished Poster Award** at Undergraduate Research Poster Presentation Workshop 2014, Department of Computer Science and Engineering, BUET for presenting a poster titled 'Many-Objective Evolutionary Approach using Fuzzy Dominance with Bidirectional Bias'.
- Inter-University Hardware Project Show Champion award for showcasing the project titled 'Cell phone operated mini-car with surveillance' at CSE festival 2013, BUET.
- Imdad-Sitara Khan Scholarship for higher-secondary studies (2006-2008) and undergraduate studies (2009-2013).
- Talent pool Board scholarship for excellence in Secondary and Higher Secondary exams, Jessore Board, Bangladesh.

REFERENCES

Available upon request